<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<interview>
    <metadata>
        <interviewer legend="J">Angelo Malamug</interviewer>
        <interviewee legend="M">Maureen Reyes</interviewee>

        <datetime>May 22, 2017, 1:53PM</datetime>
        <tags>
            <tag>Workbook guidelines</tag>
            <tag>Christian life</tag>
        </tags>
    </metadata>

    <content>
        <s legend="J">
            Have you ever skimmed or read the workbook guidelines?
        </s>
    </content>

</interview>


M: Yes
J: If so, when was the last time you use the workbook?
M: Last time I checked, chapters, during my last class, last last term? Last last last term? Third term last year.
J: So two to three terms ago?
M: tama, tama.
J: How do you use the workbook guidelines?
M” At first, every time I check a chapter. I base off of the guidelines how I comment but as I gained more experience as a faci, I understood the general gist of the guidelines so I was able to eventually comment in my own way without the guidelines although in times where I felt stumped, I fall back on the guidelines.
J: Okay, so as far as your experience in using the guidelines goes, how helpful is it? What are specific experiences that you have regarding the guideline?
M: I remember when I was a newbie, I was thankful that there was a workbook guideline because I didn’t really know how to comment. What happened was I was partnered with Joy and she was the one who commented on the first chapter so I was able to observe her commenting style. Then on the second chapter onwards, she told me “Mau, it’s your turn so you can have experience.” so at that first time that I was going to comment on a chapter, I didn’t know what to put in. And so I relied on the step by step guideline where if this is the question, this is what the question talks about, and the answer should be this. If the answer is this, you can reply using whatever is here, and it gives you tips if there was something disturbing in their answers. You can go with your choice, or you can treat them, talk to them in person, and the like.
J: So, what are some of the most difficult aspects of in terms of workbook checking? M: The number.
J: Number how? M: As in the quantity of the workbooks you need to check. But for that, if there are many facis, the number is manageable like maybe six or seven handles so you have six or seven workbooks and since it’s just a few, you’re able to focus better in commenting on each workbook but like with what happened to us last class where each facis had almost ten, you have to factor in that they’re more in count so you can’t spend as much time on one chapter for a handle.
J: Okay aside from quantity, what other aspects do you have difficulty with?
M: Sometimes when the answers are one liners. Although I tried to circumvent it by commenting with follow up question so that they are engaged and I use this policy on them when I ask follow up questions in their comments, they have to answer to me either by texting me or by pm-ing me or going to me in person. Otherwise, I don’t give next chapter. So I want to enforce this need to have communication about their responses in the workbook because I don’t want them to think of “Oh I’ll just answer it. They don’t care about what I put n here”. I want them to realize that we spend time reading what they write.
J: So in terms of quantity, how do you personally resolve that? What is your approach on that issue?
M: As much as possible what I do when there are submissions I should be ready to check them immediately. I don’t like to pile them up because I’ll get lazy and I get forced to cram comments before next week. So I do it asap since there’s going to be notifications either in canvas or in dropbox. I do my best to check it right away so that they don’t stack up.
J: Okay, what other things that we could possibly do para for quantity of handle issues, aside from what you already mentioned?
M: Aside from what I said, like not much else, I can’t think of any. Because when you’re forced to have ten to eleven handles in your group and you’re left with one week, I suppose you could schedule it, by telling them that you need to submit the workbook by this time so that you can have, let’s say three days to check like three or four in one day but aside from that, you really have no choice especially if the number of facis is hard pressed because you can’t force the student handles either to submit way before the deadline because they’re also students so the deadline that you set on a normal basis for yourself, that’s also the deadline that they’ll follow. So the facis are the ones that have to adjust.
J: Outside the scope of the workbook, what are some of the most difficult aspects of being a faci or being a believer or being a Christian in general?
M: On being a faci, I have a hard time with one on one personal interaction with handle because I’m not that comfortable with talking to people that im not that close with yet so it’s a personal quirk. But if a few terms have passed already or it’s more than midterms, I can talk to them more comfortably. Conversations aren’t as awkward and if they ask questions, I am able to share more compared to the first few weeks. For being a Christian in general, I feel like the most difficult is when other people judge you because they have this preconceived notions on what being a Christian is even if it’s not what really being a Christian is so sometimes you feel that judgment.
J; So it’s a perspective thing?
M: Yes and it hurts but usually when that happens, I take it upon myself to prove them wrong especially if their notions really are wrong.
J: Let’s say you are in a leadership position. What is your leadership style?
M: My style in general is usually to get the consensus of the group then as much as possible, when I’m the leader in a project or whatever, most often, I take the bulk of the work, either because I think that I can do it better myself or because since I feel like a leader should have more responsibilities. It’s my problem but usually I take the bulk of the work and give a bit to the other members.
J: In terms of outreach, how active were you in the outreaches.
M: With masci, when I was a newbie, Because we went to help. Mus was the one teaching back then and also Kiel. So we assisted but then there were also times that Kiel gave us the discussion on formdev part but with the actual programming, it was just either Mus or Kiel and we just helped with the activities. For outreach, I always attend whenever we have the formdev class which was always aside from this term because of conflicts so I suppose I’m more active in class outreaches compared to faci outreach.
J: In terms of your handles, how far are you willing to go for your handles? Like what was the furthest that you went for a group of people or a specific handle, or...
M: For me, not that far? As a group, I treat them so I suppose we have bonding and sharing of stories. But in the middle of the term, I’m more comfortable with dealing with them one on one or whichever handle I think needs more of my presence, and more chances to share. I focus on that so I usually pm them I aks them for their free time. So I try to get them to share because I know that some of them have issues based on their answers in the workbook. It’s there you see that they’re going through stuff but when that does happen, though I do my best to reach out it doesn’t always work because there are some handles who’ll say “No Mau, I’m fine”. So they’re not yet comfortable in sharing since there’re still walls. I still try to let them know if they ever change their mind, I would be there to listen to them and give them advice.
J: How has formdev affected or impacted on your relationships outside of DLSU?
M: With friends, there’s not much impact because, aside from formdev friends, there’s Zale, Jess, and Rag. They only know that there’s formdev so they think that you’re just busy with something. That’s what they primarily think, that there’s just a time that you’re busy. With family, I realized as a formdev faci during BS and also during reco that it affected me because I’d like to say that I became a better daughter. Although I can’t say for sure but I feel like there’s a change that’s really happening, and its for the better and I’m happy about it.
J: And what would that specific change be, if you could elaborate.
M: I am more appreciative of the love my parents give me, and that I’m more able to relate it to the love that God gives me. Because before, it’s like they’re there but the feeling is not close. But now I know that they are there for me and I am here to be there for them as well. It’s not that complete but it affects in little ways like for instance, in times when they ask me to do something, I have more of the initiative to do the tasks since it was one of my frequent apps
during my first few BS sessions, to the point that I no longer need to be nagged for much long before I do it.
J: so last question, what was the most significant change that formdev has brought out in you>
M: Personally, character development because before formdev, I’m still not comfortable with speaking in front of people but I’d say that formdev has helped me to at least be somewhat comfortable with it that I know that if I did not join formdev, I’d still be shy and I’d still not have the will to talk to people and share.
J: So you’re bolder now?
M: Yes, I’m more able to share experiences, I am more able to witness to other people, That’s one of the reasons in my application, and I mentioned it that one of my reasons for joining formdev is to learn how to witness because I really couldn’t do it because of either I find it hard to talk to strangers or lack of my reflections and experiences but in joining formdev, somewhat it added to what was once lacking.